Guide to the Mark Naison papers 2016.021
Brooklyn Historical Society
Mark Naison papers
1931-2011
Brooklyn Historical Society
Naison, Mark D., 1946-
2016.021
11 Linear Feet in nineteen manuscript boxes and one oversize box
0.07 Megabytes in 16 digital files
The collection contains the papers of Mark Naison, including correspondence, typescripts, publications, student work, research files, organizational records, and photographs, dating from 1931 to 2011. On the whole, they document his life as a student, teacher, historian, writer, activist, and sports enthusiast. Naison, who was born and resided in Brooklyn for most of his life, is a professor of African and African American Studies at Fordham University.
Conditions Governing Access
Student papers written by the recording artist Lana Del Ray in Box 12 are restricted for 75 years from their date of creation for privacy reasons (2083).
Copies of the CrossBronx Express newspaper are in fragile condition. Please use the preservation photocopies provided in place of the originals.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the papers of Mark Naison, including correspondence, typescripts, publications, student work, research files, organizational records, and photographs, dating from 1931 to 2011. On the whole, they document his life as a student, teacher, historian, writer, activist, and sports enthusiast.
Arrangement
The papers are organized into seven series:
Series 1: Columbia University student papers document Naison's time as an undergraduate and graduate student, and includes his master's essay on the Southern Tenant Farmers' Union.
Series 2: Writings contains files relating to various works by Naison, including his memoir.
Series 3: Correspondence includes both professional and personal correspondence and touch upon many issues from the other series.
Series 4: Professional papers document Naison's role as a teacher and historian.
Series 5: Save A Generation records contains files relating to the Bronx-based community organization.
Series 6: Sports files document Naison's passion for athletics, and includess a number of organizations that he has been involved in, such as Sports for the People, the 78th Precinct Youth Council, C.A.R.E., F.A.N.S., and the Bonnie Youth Club. It also includes files on his children's youth sports careers.
Series 7: Personal photographs and papers includes Naison's bar mitzvah photographs and some papers relating to his activism in the Bronx.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mark Naison papers, 2016.
Related Materials
Other collections held by BHS relating to community activism include:
Eastern Parkway Coalition records (2007.016)
Sarita Daftary-Steel collection of East New York oral histories (2015.011)
Arnie Goldwag Brooklyn Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) collection (ARC.002)
Bob Adelman photographs of Brooklyn Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) demonstrations (V1989.022)
Biographical note
Mark Naison is an educator, writer, historian, and community activist. He was born in 1946 to Jewish parents and spent his youth in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. He attended Columbia University, where he received his BA, MA, and PhD. He has been a professor at Fordham University since 1970 and was a founding faculty member of their African American studies program, where he remains to this day. He has been a member of numerous progressive and community-based organizations throughout his life, including the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE), Sports for the People, Save a Generation, and the Bad Ass Teachers Association. According to his Fordham University biography, " he is the author of six books and over 300 articles on African American politics, labor history, popular culture and education policy." He has two children and has lived in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn for over thirty years.
Sources:
"Mark Naison," Fordham University, accessed December 13, 2016. "http://www.fordham.edu/info/22662/faculty/4489/mark_naison">http://www.fordham.edu/info/22662/faculty/4489/mark_naison.
In these times; African-American studies; Authors, American |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bar mitzvah; Basketball |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Clippings (information artifacts); College teachers |z New York (State); Communism |x African Americans; Community activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Correspondence; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Diaries; Floppy disks; Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Historians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews, American |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parade Grounds (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Photographs; Publishers and publishing; Research notes; Sports |z United States |y 20th century; Sports for children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Tennis |z United States; Typescripts; Berkeley Carroll School; Berry, Abner W.; Center for Athletes Rights and Education (C.A.R.E.); Columbia University; F.A.N.S. (Sports activist organization); Fordham University. African and African American Studies; Genovese, Eugene D.; Naison, Mark D., 1946-; Organization of American Historians; Robeson, Paul; Save A Generation (Bronx, New York, N.Y.); Southern Tenant Farmers' Union; Sports for the People (Bronx, New York, N.Y.); USTA National Junior Tennis League
- Series 1: Columbia University student papers, 1931-circa 1976; 66782; 1 Linear Feet in two manuscript boxes
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged in the following order: undergradate files, master's thesis files, and dissertation files.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains files relating to Naison's undergradate and graduate-level education at Columbia University, dating from 1931 to circa 1976. The bulk of the files relate to his class work, especially his master's essay and his dissertation. The topics of these papers are the Southern Tenant Farmers' Union and the relationship between African Americans and American Communists. The files consist of typescripts of his master's essay, correspondence, and research files for both papers (including primary sources dating back to the 1930s). Additionally, the series contains clippings documenting Naison's role as captain of the school's tennis team and other ephemera.
  - Columbia University student papers (Box 1)
  - Columbia University student papers (Box 2)
- Series 2: Writings, 1969-2008; 66783; 3 Linear Feet in eight manuscript boxes
  The series contains files relating to Naison's writings, both published and unpublished, dating from 1969 to 2008. In addition to his memoir and poetry, the writings also cover American sports and the relationship between American communists and African Americans. The files include typescripts, clippings, correspondence, and related documents.
  Documents relating to his writings can be found in Series 3: Correspondence and Series 4: Professional papers.
  The series is arranged into three sub-series:
  Sub-series 2.1: Writings on communism
  Sub-series 2.2: White Boy: A Memoir
  Sub-series 2.3: Articles and other works
  - Sub-series 2.1: Writings on communism, 1973-1989; 66784; 0.6 Linear Feet in one manuscript box and two folders
    Arranged chronologically.
    The sub-series contains files relating to Naison's writings on communism in the United States, specifically Communists in Harlem During the Depression and an unpublished history of American communism, dating from 1973 to 1989. It includes manuscripts, correspondence, contracts, clippings, and research files. Of note are transcripts of interviews with Harlem Communist Party organizer and The Daily Worker editor Abner Berry.
    Naison's dissertation was also on African Americans and the Communist Party, and files relating to that work can be found in Series 1: Columbia University student papers.
    - Writings on communism (Box 3)
    - Writings on communism (Box 4)
  - Sub-series 2.2: White Boy: A Memoir, 1995-2005; 66785; 1.8 Linear Feet in four manuscript boxes
    The sub-series contains files relating to Naison's White Boy: A Memoir, dating from 1995 to 2005. It includes typescripts, correspondence, clippings, speeches, publicity material, one 3.5" floppy disk, and other files.
    One additional file, labeled "Black Studies (material relevant to White Boy)" is located in Series 4: Professional papers.
    - White Boy: A Memoir (Box 4)
    - White Boy: A Memoir (Box 5)
    - White Boy: A Memoir (Box 6)
    - White Boy: A Memoir (Box 7)
    - White Boy: A Memoir Word Perfect files (digital files)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Donated on one 3.5 inch floppy disk, containing 14 Word Perfect files. Digital ID 2016_021_media_001.
      Conditions Governing Access
      Access to digital materials is available onsite at the Othmer Library. Requests to access digital materials must be made at least 2 days in advance by emailing library@brooklynhistory.org.
  - Sub-series 2.3: Articles and other works, 1969-2008; 66786; 0.6 Linear Feet in one manuscript box and four folders
    The sub-series is comprised of articles, poems, book reviews, and other writings by Naison, dating from 1969 to 2008. It includes many articles written on sports, mostly for the publication In These Times, as well as pieces on race, labor, politics, education, and other subjects.
    - Articles and other works (Box 7)
    - Articles and other works (Box 8)
- Series 3: Correspondence, 1965-2005; 66787; 1.1 Linear Feet in two manuscript boxes and two folders
  The series contains correspondence to and from Naison, dating from 1965 to 2005. It covers both his personal and professional lives. It includes correspondence with historian Eugene Genovese and activist Ray Reece, among many others.
  - Correspondence (Box 8)
  - Correspondence (Box 9)
  - Correspondence (Box 10)
- Series 4: Professional papers, 1967-2008; 66788; 1 Linear Feet in two mansucript boxes and five folders
  The series is comprised of documents relating to Naison's career as a historian and educator, dating from 1967 to 2008. It includes files related to job searches, recommendations, writing for Radical America and The Journal of Ethnic Studies, the African American studies program at Fordham University, the Mid-Atlantic Radical Historians Organization, and the Organization of American Historians (OAH). This includes files on the protest against the Adams Mark Hotel in St. Louis (the site of the 2000 OAH annual meeting) for their record of discriminating against Black employees and guests. It also includes files relating to an exhibition honoring Paul Robeson and one file of student papers written by the recording artist Lana Del Ray (restricted for privacy reasons until 2083).
  - Professional papers (Box 10)
  - Professional papers (Box 11)
  - Professional papers (Box 12)
- Series 5: Save A Generation records, 1990-1996; 66790; 0.5 Linear Feet in nine folders
  The series contains files relating to the Bronx Youth Conservation Corps' Save a Generation program, dating from 1990 to 1996. The files include meeting minutes, clippings, reports, and correspondence. The program was established to provide job and educational services to at-risk youth in the Bronx. Naison served on the organization's board from its establishment in 1990 until 1996.
  Additional records relating to community activism in the Bronx can be found in Series 7: Personal photographs and papers.
  - Save A Generation records (Box 12)
  - Save A Generation records (Box 13)
- Series 6: Sports files, 1970-2000; 66791; 3 Linear Feet in seven manuscript boxes
  The series is organized into five sub-series:
  Sub-series 6.1: Sports for the People records
  Sub-series 6.2: Sports research files
  Sub-series 6.3: Family sports records
  Sub-series 6.4: 78th Precinct Youth Sports Council records
  Sub-series 6.5: Miscellaneous sports files
  The series documents Naison's passion for athletics, and includes a number of organizations that he has been involved in, such as Sports for the People, the 78th Precinct Youth Council, C.A.R.E., F.A.N.S., and the Bonnie Youth Club. It also includes files on his children's youth sports careers.
  For Naison's writings on sports, see: Sub-series 2.3: Articles and other works.
  - Sub-series 6.1: Sports for the People records, 1974-1992; 66792; 0.9 Linear Feet in two manuscript boxes and two folders
    The sub-series contains files relating to Sports for the People (SFTP) and includes board minutes, legal documents, correspondence, reports, clippings, and other files, dating from 1974 to 1992. The organization was established to promote sports as right for all. Naison served on the SFTP's board and the files document the organization from its beginnings through its dissolution due to a financial crisis in the 1980s. Other organizations, such as the Center For Athletes Rights and Education (C.A.R.E) and the National Football League Players Association (NFLPA), are included among the files.
    - Sports for the People records (Box 13)
    - Sports for the People records (Box 14)
    - Sports for the People records (Box 15)
  - Sub-series 6.2: Sports research files, 1973-1982; 66793; 0.5 Linear Feet in one manuscript box and ten folders
    The sub-series consists of research files on sports compiled by Naison, dating from 1973 to 1982. It includes articles, correspondence, interview transcripts, and files on sports-related courses taught by Naison at Fordham University.
    - Sports research files (Box 15)
    - Sports research files (Box 16)
  - Sub-series 6.3: Family sports records, 1986-1999; 66794; 0.8 Linear Feet in two manuscript boxes
    The sub-series contains records relating to the sports careers of the Naison family, dating from 1986 to 1999. It includes diaries, clippings, photographs, ephemera, and other records. Naison coached youth sports, his daughter Sara Naison-Phillips played tennis and basketball, and his son Eric Naison played baseball and basketball. Sara was a USTA ranked youth tennis player and Eric was a star baseball player for the Berkeley Carroll school.
    The sub-series is arranged in the following order: family sports diaries, Sara Naison-Phillips records, and Eric Naison records.
    - Family sports records (Box 16)
    - Family sports records (Box 17)
  - Sub-series 6.4: 78th Precinct Youth Sports Council records, 1987-1997; 66795; 0.6 Linear Feet in one manuscript box and two folders
    The sub-series contains records of the 78th Precinct Youth Sports Council records, a non-profit Brooklyn-based youth sports organization, dating from 1987 to 1988. Naison was both a coach and board member and the records include board meeting minutes, correspondence, team scorecards, by-laws and certificates of incorporation, clippings, and photographs. The organization was originally established as St. Savior's Youth Council, and the records document the break between the Youth Council and St. Savior's Catholic Church.
    - 78th Precinct Youth Sports Council records (Box 17)
    - 78th Precinct Youth Sports Council records (Box 18)
  - Sub-series 6.5: Miscellaneous sports files, 1970-2000; 66796; 0.2 Linear Feet in five folders; Arranged chronologically.
    The sub-series contains a small amount of sports related files that did not fit into any of the other sub-series. It includes files on F.A.N.S. (The Fight to Advance the Nation's Sports) (1970-1980), a panel on race and sports (1980), clippings (1982-1983), and the Bonnie Youth Club baseball team/revitization of the Parade Grounds (circa 1997-2000).
    - Miscellaneous sports files (Box 19)
- Series 7: Personal photographs and papers, 1959-2011; 66797; 1.4 Linear Feet in seven folders and two oversize folders
  Arranged chronologically. The cover to Naison's bar mitzvah photograph album and original issues of the CrossBronx Express newspaper are stored in box OS-20.
  The series contains assorted files relating to Naison's personal life, dating from 1959 to 2011. It includes photographs of Naison's bar mitzvah (1959), the cover of the photograph album that housed the bar mitzvah photographs, family photographs found loose in that album (circa 1960s-circa 1970s), two issues of the CrossBronx Express (1970, an activist newspaper published by Bronx People), a file on landlord-tenant issues for Naison's apartment at 317 West 99th street, Manhattan (1970s), a file on the Fordham-Bedford Housing Association (1985-1989), photographs of a police brutality protest (2000), and a New York State Assembly certificate honoring Naison (2011).
  - Personal photographs and papers (Box 19)
  - Personal photographs and papers (Box OS-20)